<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on A Blog</title>
    <link>http://nii236.github.io/technical-blog/tags/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on A Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 14:30:07 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://nii236.github.io/technical-blog/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Elixir</title>
      <link>http://nii236.github.io/technical-blog/post/elixir/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 14:30:07 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nii236.github.io/technical-blog/post/elixir/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;All this Gophering around can get boring. That&amp;rsquo;s not a bad thing, I still consider Go the language with which I am strongest and most comfortable. If I had to use a language at my workplace, Go would be it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes you just want to poke around and see what else is out there. A language that offers a sense of adventure instead of the safety of Go and its static types, simplicity, rock solid linting and strict philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;elixir-lang.org&#34;&gt;Elixir&lt;/a&gt; complements Go in this regard. In fact it seems to be the complete opposite. Loosely typed, immutable data structures, enumerators, functional style programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, apparently functional programming is a cool hip thing to do nowadays. Its a fancy term, it makes you think that functional programming actually works (you know, its &lt;em&gt;FUNCTIONAL&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I play around with linux/unix/osx (hah!) a lot, and the fact that you have a pipeline operator Elixir is amazing! Also map, reduce, filter and each operators are something I miss a lot moving to Go from Ruby, so I&amp;rsquo;m glad to see that it&amp;rsquo;s got the first class treatment here in Elixir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;n-ot-i-nvented-h-ere:d357eede9a990435baf8e64347147ff3&#34;&gt;N(ot) I(nvented) H(ere)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in Go land for so long, I had forgotten what the rest of the programming world is like. Gopher&amp;rsquo;s shun extending the language, using dependencies, building packages for others to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gopher&amp;rsquo;s have a serious case of NIH syndrome, and everything is handrolled to extremes. Its actually quite nice if you think about it. The software you develop ends up fitting like a really, really tight glove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was, however, still an (unexpected) breath of fresh air when I had a look at the Elixir community and how they were enthusiastically talking about writing macros, extending the language, using web frameworks and installing dependencies willy nilly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;code:d357eede9a990435baf8e64347147ff3&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I figured as a raw exercise, to convert one of the easy katas I did long ago. The exercise is called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hackerrank.com/challenges/cut-the-sticks&#34;&gt;Cut the Sticks&lt;/a&gt; and is a good exercise in recursion (my Go solution did not, however, use recursion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;processing-stdin:d357eede9a990435baf8e64347147ff3&#34;&gt;Processing STDIN&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest part in Go is always processing the arguments that come through HackerRank. Lots of STDIN scanning, processing etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how I processed the STDIN with Go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Go&#34;&gt;// GetArgs reads from STDIN and returns stuff in the correct format
func GetArgs(r io.Reader) (int, []int) {
	var numArgs = 0
	_, err := fmt.Fscanln(r, &amp;amp;numArgs)

	if err != nil {
		fmt.Println(err)
	}

	sumArgs := make([]int, numArgs)
	for i := range sumArgs {
		_, err = fmt.Fscan(r, &amp;amp;sumArgs[i])
		if err != nil {
			fmt.Println(err)
		}
	}

	return numArgs, sumArgs
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is in Elixir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def process(input) do
  values = String.split(input, &amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;)
    |&amp;gt; List.delete_at(0)
    |&amp;gt; List.delete_at(-1)
    |&amp;gt; List.to_string
    |&amp;gt; String.strip
    |&amp;gt; String.split(&amp;quot; &amp;quot;)
    |&amp;gt; Enum.map(&amp;amp;(Integer.parse(&amp;amp;1)))
    |&amp;gt; Enum.map(&amp;amp;(elem(&amp;amp;1,0)))
  recurse_cut(values, Enum.max(values))
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I just suck at Go, but I dunno, there&amp;rsquo;s just something really, really &lt;strong&gt;satisfying&lt;/strong&gt; about the pipeline operator and processing stuff functionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cutting-the-sticks:d357eede9a990435baf8e64347147ff3&#34;&gt;Cutting the sticks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; code involves chopping off the sticks by the length of the shortest stick until nothing remains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: I had a look and turns out I wrote the Go code recursively after all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is in Go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;func cut(numArgs int, args []int, finalArray []int) (int, []int, []int) {

	var newArray []int
	var newFinalArray []int
	var zeroValue bool

	minArg := args[0]

	// Get smallest number in args
	for _, arg := range args {
		if arg &amp;lt; minArg {
			minArg = arg
		}
		if arg == 0 {
			zeroValue = true
		}
	}

	// If non zero, append to resulting array, less the minimum arg
	for _, arg := range args {
		if arg != 0 {
			newArray = append(newArray, arg-minArg)
		}
	}

	// If there exists any zero length sticks, run function again
	if zeroValue {
		return cut(len(newArray), newArray, finalArray)
	}

	// If more than 1 stick remain, run function recursively
	if numArgs &amp;gt; 1 {
		newFinalArray = append(finalArray, len(newArray))
		return cut(len(newArray), newArray, newFinalArray)
	}

	newFinalArray = append(finalArray, len(newArray))
	return len(newArray), newArray, newFinalArray

}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is in Elixir:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  def recurse_cut(values, max) when max &amp;gt; 0 do
    min = values
      |&amp;gt; Enum.filter(&amp;amp;(&amp;amp;1 &amp;gt; 0))
      |&amp;gt; Enum.min
    IO.puts(Enum.count(values, &amp;amp;(&amp;amp;1 &amp;gt;= min)))
    result = Enum.map(values, &amp;amp;(&amp;amp;1-min))
    recurse_cut(result, Enum.max(result))
  end

  def recurse_cut(_values, max) when max &amp;lt;= 0 do
  end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its so clean!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, for programs that require a lot of iteration and mucking about, you might find that a functional style is a lot more efficient, and easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still believe Go has advantages in tooling, raw speed, simplicity, teams, documentation and a unified community vision. But Elixir offers a great functional style of programming and a sense of adventure that complements it very nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t explored Elixir&amp;rsquo;s metaprogramming, macros or concurrency yet. I will have a look and share my thoughts in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>npm install mad-skillz</title>
      <link>http://nii236.github.io/technical-blog/post/jobprep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 11:06:25 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nii236.github.io/technical-blog/post/jobprep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I started considering a job in software development around October 2014. All I had with me were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First year computer science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechatronics engineering (MATLAB and similar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two years of PLC/SCADA/Cicode programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9 months of being stuck on site and poking around with Linux, VPNs, vim, bash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not too bad considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a extremely large appetite for self learning and research if something interests me enough, so for the next few months I applied for various software roles, while self learning. Codecademy, The Odin Project, The Rails Tutorial were part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, applying to more control systems jobs was my other fulltime job. You know, in addition to my existing fulltime job of trying to be a software developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose I lucked out in the end. I managed to score a role at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thefrontiergroup.com.au&#34;&gt;The Frontier Group&lt;/a&gt;! At the end of the day, it was not my feeble attempts to learn software development that got me the role, it was a combination of the following things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The drive to learn something new&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The initiative to switch careers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to fit into the company culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My existing knowledge in mining and engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual role was not a development role unfortunately. I was employed as an &amp;lsquo;analyst developer&amp;rsquo;, which focuses on data analytics for various clients (usually mining). TFG is, however, mainly a web development company, and I hoped by just being I would have the opportunity to learn skills that I needed to be able to hold my own in this new industry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>